All right, everybody.
We are getting to that time.
So I just want to say hello.
Hello, hello.
Thank you for coming out early or late
or wherever you are in
time to our panel today for ello 26.
This is the hypertext and Fictions panel.
And we got a great line up for you
this morning with
yeah, so nice to meet so many friends.
And that was one thing
that I've been remarking on
to anyone who will listen all week so far
is how shocked I am that even yellow over
zoom can be a great time.
I thought that I was just really spoiled
last year in Toronto,
but this has been a great time.
Toronto was awesome.
Yeah, but the way that we're handling
this, we have four papers.
Everybody is going to give
about 15 minutes to go.
And I've already gone over
some of the notices
with some of our panelists.
So without further ado, I will allow
Gisella de Castro to introduce herself.
Thank you. Gisella.
Yoda.
Hello. Good morning. Good night.
Good evening.
I will share my screen.
Just a minute.
In this way is okay for you.
Looks great.
All right.
So. Okay.
I'm Castro,
I'm a PhD candidate at the University
of Waikato, New Zealand in the Screen
and Media Studies program, School of Arts.
And my supervisors are Doctor
Lisa Parrott and Doctor Hill.
I will present the paper a
Z a flight of Art and New Zealand
Epistolary
Electronic Literature
in an interactive video book for children.
I'm from Rio de Janeiro, Brazil,
and this is my stunning city
with my mountain,
my forest, my river, my ocean,
my Atlantic Ocean.
My first language is Portuguese, so
I'm learning English alongside my PhD.
Please be kind with some grammar issues
and A40 and Z is a PhD motor model.
Research creation.
My topic is the creative processes
to address
the intersection between geography
and electronic literature.
My approach is remediating by reaffirming
children's
letters on a digital reading platform.
So A14 Z is an interactive video book
based on children's letters
about their places in Ottawa, New Zealand.
I don't know if you know this name out
there is the indigenous name
of the country.
So this is a bike, bike
or two road nation.
So I'm respecting the indigenous
aspect of the country.
Where did this idea come from?
In 2019, I published a book.
A collection of books, indeed
five books that form
a map of Brazil as a puzzle,
as you can see.
And during the Covid pandemic,
I was doing my Masters
in Creative Media online.
In strictly lockdown, and I considered
how can access books
without libraries or schools?
And what about children
who don't have books at home?
So I developed an interactive video book
with the same content with the publicity
one, and I did a Brazilian sign
language translation to allow people
with some hearing payments
to, to leverage
and enjoy the same content.
And it was I received the prize
in the Brazilian capital in the literature
for people with disabilities category
and do proposing my PhD.
I considered a digital book that would
make sense in Ottawa, New Zealand.
So I, I come back to my
memories, my childhood memories,
and I keep this with me until now.
This is my first book in life.
I'm a writer and publisher nowadays,
but in this time I was six years old
and I wrote this, The Werewolf.
And as well I kept this.
My statement from 1985
talking about the idea of city.
The city of desires.
I remember the sensation
to to write an essay
about the perfect city,
the issues involved.
And it was inspired in a very successful
theater play in Brazil,
banks based on the music and
the four musicians of Bremen,
Bremen in Italian and the the.
The main song about this talk at
it was about the City of Desires.
And then I invited the students
in New Zealand
to write letters about their cities,
asking the students to write.
Answering this question,
what would you say to your region
if it were a person?
And when I invite students
to write letters, sometimes they said, oh,
I don't know how to write.
I have no ideas.
I don't like to write.
And then I explain them.
This idea of love was is law.
I don't know if you know this quotation.
The sentences,
this sentence was attributed
to him as a researcher.
He was talking
about the conservation of matter
or the conservation of mass in chemistry,
and he supposedly said, nothing is lost,
nothing is created,
everything is transformed.
And then I talk this to them.
Cuphead, the video game and
then was transformed in Netflix show
and and the team.
The motto, the light motif of the video
game is don't deal with the devil.
And the motto is the same of South
to written by goods
in 1808 and don't deal with the devil.
It's the same theme
and there are statics of
the couple had reminds me, Felix the Cat,
and as well
this on the bottom is the second short
movie made by Walt Disney
as well, inspired by Die Bremer.
The formulations of Bremer, the animals
and this tale
are published by Brothers Grimm
was a inspired
by a storyteller, Dorothea Vermeer,
and Before the Green,
the Brothers Grimm published this.
So one thing can bring
another and another and another.
And to explain to my own
supervisors and the students as well,
my methodology in transdisciplinary
and multiple references,
I will seek seeking a
research creation methodology
inspired by this long play created by you.
Parabolic camera is analogies
mixing two words parabolic from parabolic
antenna and camera is called
a Jewish convocation is claiming
for this parabolic comrade
to create something new,
and this cover of the LP
is very iconic to me
because this indigenous basket
is a similar room of a parabolic antenna
is pretending to be a parabolic antenna.
So I used to say I am using AI
as ancestral intelligence
to reimagine a technological future.
And this was my first experiment
to explain
how is the process of remediating letters
by mixing documentary, fiction
and animation approaches
in a combination of terrorism procedures
to create a new form of reading,
at least close reading,
not distant reading.
And this was the first letter
collected from a girl six years old.
She was learning how to write, probably,
and the sentences was difficult
to decipher.
The calligraphy, the handwritten text.
So we transformed these sentences in a
audio vision production.
Can you see and listen?
I don't know if the sound is running.
We can't hear the sound now.
No worries. That sound is.
It doesn't matter so perfectly.
I will read for you.
Why aren't kids allowed to drink alcohol?
Do you know why?
Well, I think I might know why.
I think it has something
that makes kids hype up.
And this transformation
of the letter from Francis
was the first experiment
to to to show as an example,
as a sample to,
to the process of transformation.
And I received so many letters
in different ways.
Sometimes they had drawings,
sometimes I received the letter
via discord, read,
written or typed in email.
So I called this process of forming
because I was matching the format
of the letter, the content of the letter
with the skills of the animators,
the collaborators and the volunteers.
And I collected 70 letters,
transformed into 22 videos
with seven animators,
three musicians, one art design
process, one app designer,
one editor and proofreader, a voice actor
and a technical consultant.
And I will read the sentence.
I called the process forming letters
inspired by the theater of the oppressed,
developed by August Blow,
the collaborative team from New Zealand,
Canada and Brazil
played in dialog with the stimuli
provided by children's letters
with improvization flexibility,
openness and freedom
in challenging time zones as well.
And to conclude,
decoration
phase was the important point to I was.
I will read this sentence as well.
Given the genitive of the letters
and the creators diverse styles,
we had to work a collaboratively
to achieve a static unity
and cohesive visual identity.
And then I discovered
this bird, the fairy turn.
Charity is the name of the bird, one of
the most endangered bird in New Zealand,
as a symbol, as an avatar of the platform,
to bring the environmental awareness to
to the to the landscape of the
the home page
and mixing
handcrafted and digital art
and inspired by artists.
Contemporary female artists
like Annabella Geiger,
Sheila Hicks and Alexandra Kahlo.
I could developed these pieces
of my puzzle with wool,
fabric and soft materials
to because I don't know how to paint.
I don't know how to create a digital art,
but handcrafted materials I can do.
And then I mix this with the web designer
to create this kind of careless softness,
coziness to the to the home page.
And I put this symbol to activate
voice over.
I don't know if you can see the symbol
here because we discovered the letters,
the audio visualizing
way of reading the letters.
Sometimes what was difficult to
because they went reading
or the subtitles were so fast,
and children who don't know how to read,
or people with a kind of
cognitive impairment or visual impairment
can enjoy the same content
with this activated voice over.
But you can turn off if you want to read
and listen to the music in the soundtrack
or the original sound,
the diverse of sounds by yourselves
and Gisella,
I will say you have about one minute left.
Yeah, this is the last one.
And the we create a time capsule
to put the original letters as well.
So you can click on the region
and watch the video
or read the letter in the time capsule.
If you want to contact me, I will have
I will be happy to contact you as well.
Thank you.